Tokyo's additional insurance policy is
what Mireya Solis of the Brookings
Institution describes as a strategy of
becoming a network power. The goal is
not to create an Asian NATO or some
regional block capable of replacing the
United States. Rather, the idea is to
build on the US-Japan alliance through
close cooperation with other regional
partners that share an interest in
preserving the American presence in Asia
and balancing China.
Cooperation has gone furthest with
Australia. The two countries conduct
military exercises, cooperate on defense
industry [music] projects, and their
reciprocal access agreement in force
since 2023 makes it easier for their
armed forces to operate on each other's
territory. The Philippines plays a
different role. Its islands form the
southern section of the first island
chain and the guard the Luzon Strait.
Japan supplies the Philippines with
radar systems, strengthens its Coast
Guard, and an agreement in force since
2025 facilitates joint exercises. South
Korea contributes highly capable armed
forces, advanced intelligence and
surveillance systems, and the critical
position on the region's northeastern
flank. India extends the network into
the Indian Ocean, while the Quad
provides a framework for coordinating
maritime security, infrastructure, and
supply chain resilience. European
partners, meanwhile, contribute
technology, weapons, and political
support for freedom of navigation.